Guide to the Romyn Hitchcock papers, 1841-1900.
Hitchcock, Romyn papers, 1841-1900.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Romyn Hitchcock papers, 1841-1900, 1882-1900 (bulk).
2174
Romyn Hitchcock, 1851-1923.
.3 cubic ft.
Correspondence, lecture notes, monographs, government bulletins and other pamphlet material, newspaper clippings, and maps.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers of Romyn Hitchcock, a chemist and lecturer on the Orient, include correspondence, lecture notes, monographs, government bulletins and other pamphlet material, newspaper clippings, and maps. Collection is primarily concerned with Chinese-American diplomatic relations; spheres of influence; problems of Chinese immigration, including low wages, tong societies, and the Chinese Exclusion Act; and the geography, art, religion, and customs of China and Japan.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers of Romyn Hitchcock, a chemist and lecturer on the Orient, include correspondence, lecture notes, monographs, government bulletins and other pamphlet material, newspaper clippings, and maps. Collection is primarily concerned with Chinese-American diplomatic relations; spheres of influence; problems of Chinese immigration, including low wages, tong societies, and the Chinese Exclusion Act; and the geography, art, religion, and customs of China and Japan.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Hitchcock, Romyn, 1851-1923.
Subjects:
Art--China.; Art--Japan.; Emigration and immigration.; International relations.; Sinologists.
Places:
China--Religion.; Japan--Religion.; China--Description and travel.; China--Emigration and immigration.; China--Foreign relations.; Japan--Description and travel.; United States--Emigration and immigration.; United States--Foreign relations.
Form and Genre Terms:
Maps.; Lecture notes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- A. Brown Hard Cover Notebook entitled "China Miscellany" (Box 1)
  Contains articles on China taken from various magazines with two articles by Hitchcock; "The Great Wall of China," and "Chinese Education" taken from Century Magazin, Oct. 1900; also article, "An Inquiry into the Population of China," by William Woodville Rockhill, and one entitled "The Peking Legations," by Sir Robert Hart, as well as nine others.
- B. Speeches, correspondence, etc.
  - 1. Introduction to a lecture given to the Friday Club - a very brief historical sketch of China. (Box 1)
  - 2. Minutes of Tientsin Literary and Debating Society where Hitchcock gave a lecture on the Ainos [Ainus] of Yezo. (2 copies) (Box 1)
  - 3. Letter, apparently in answer to a letter Hitchcock wrote to the Jap Mail, May 21, 1888 on Japanese education. (Box 1)
- C. Newspaper clippings
  - 1. Chinese customs - art by Hitchcock in Washington Evening Star, June 20, 1891. (Box 1)
  - 2. Great Wall of China - article by Hitchcock in National Tribune, Nov. 17, 1892. (Box 1)
  - 3. Proposed cable between U.S. and China - Hitchcock's project. (Box 1)
  - 4. Chinese Politics - article by Hitchcock - possibility of revolution - unrest, group of conspirators in the North; Imperial government very weak. (Box 1)
  - 5. Early Peoples of Japan - article by Hitchcock - the pit dwellers who now live on Shikotan. (Box 1)
  - 6. Article on proposed Chinese exhibit at International Exposition and what it could contain. North China Daily News, July 21, 1891 (2 copies). (Box 1)
  - 7. Native American foodstuffs and their importance in the world. Article by Hitchcock in North China Daily News, July 3, 1891. (Box 1)
  - 8. Chicago World's Fair, Article by H. in Chinese Times, Jan. 30, 1891. (Box 1)
  - 9. Telegraph lines and Railways in China, article by H. in Engineering News, Nov. 17, 1892. (Box 1)
  - 10. Facts about the Ainos [Ainus] of Yezo: an article by H. in the Washington Star, Mar. 15, 1890. (Box 1)
  - 11. Struggle over question of Chinese Consulate in Hong Kong, July 24, 1891. (Box 1)
  - 12. Chinese courts and treatment of Chinese by other nations, Feb. 7, 1891. (Box 1)
  - 13. Problem of policing Hunan Province after Boxer Rebellion, 1891, North China Herald. (Box 1)
  - 14. Articles on Consuls in China (Box 1)
  - 15. Imperial audience at court of Peking, Mar. 5, 1891. (Box 1)
  - 16. More about audience, Mar. 14, 1891. (Box 1)
  - 17. Speeches of von Brandt and of Emperor at audience, Mar. 14, 1891. (Box 1)
  - 18. Articles about the phoenix and about ancient art in China. (Box 1)
  - 19. Broadside on Customs Courier Service: Winter 1891-1892 (Box 1)
  - 20. "Journeys in the Pamirs and Adjacent Countries" in Science, Feb. 26, 1892. (Box 1)
  - 21. Article on quicksilver and vermilion in China. (Box 1)
  - 22. Agricultural history of China - article in North China Daily News, Sept. 11, 1890. (Box 1)
  - 23. Political position of the Liukiu Islands. (Box 1)
  - 24. Development of Tongking (French Indo-China) - article in Chinese Times, Feb. 7, 1891. (Box 1)
  - 25. Wolesey in China - Chinese Times, Dec. 13, 1890. (Box 1)
  - 26. Article on Formosa in Shanghai Mercury, June 13, 1891. (Box 1)
- D. Translation of a Memorial from Li Hung-Chang to the Throne on the Floods in Chihli, Aug. 4, 1890. (Box 1)
- E. Maps
  - 1. Russian Empire with explanation in Russian, 1890, 12" x 20". (Box 1)
  - 2. Formosa, 1890, Issued by North China Daily News, 15" x 10 1/2". (Box 1)
  - 3. Yun-Nan with explanation in French, 1891, The Shanghai Chromo. & Photo Litho. Co., Ltd., 2' 4" x 2'. (Box 1)
  - 4. Philips Map of Asia, undated, George Philip & Son, 26" x 22", (Bound in paper). (Box 1)
- F. Pamphlets
  - 1. Reports from the Consuls of the U.S. - one on Chinese curios, Dec. 1892. (Box 1)
  - 2. "The Chinaman as a Laborer" - pamphlet against exclusion of Chinese from U.S., Feb. 27, 1882. (Box 1)
  - 3. "The Preparation of Japanese Lacquer ..." - article in Proceedings of U.S. National Museum, by H.; 2 copies, 1889. (Box 1)
  - 4. Appeal to the Senate on subject of Chinese immigration - wants it controlled but not total exclusion, by H., Feb. 9, 1892. (Box 1)
  - 5. Report of the Secretary of State on the subject of political relations between the U.S. and China - documents, 1790-1840 (1841). (Box 1)
  - 6. 3 circulars about Chinese coming into U.S.; Aug. 1, 1891; Aug. 18, 1892; Sept. 1, 1892. (Box 1)
  - 7. Immigration forbidding Chinese, 1892. (Box 1)
  - 8. Census Bulletin, July 14, 1892 - "Colored Population in 1890." (Box 1)
  - 9. Article from The Californian, Jan. 1892 about the Tong Societies. (Box 1)
  - 10. "American Influence in China," by John R. Young. (Box 1)
  - 11. Article on Supreme Court Case over constitutionality of Geary Act, California Mag. (Box 1)
  - 12. The Law and the Chinaman, by Thomas J. Geary - pro-exclusion. (Box 1)
- G. Correspondence
  - 1. To R. Hitchcock from H.D. Paul (a lawyer) about getting parts of the Chinese Exclusion Act changed, Aug. 18, 1892. (Box 1)
  - 2. To Hitchcock from Managing Director of Imperial Chinese Railways:
    - a) Nov. 1., 1891 - a polite answer (Box 1)
    - b) Jan. 26, 1893 - about an American engineer looking for work on the railroad (Box 1)
    - c) Mar. 5, 1893 - Progress of RR., status of Americans in China since Exclusion Act passed. (Box 1)
  - 3. To Hon. J.N. Dolph, U.S. Senate from Hitchcock - rough draft of a letter to his senator deploring the Chinese Exclusion Act. (Box 1)
- H. Lectures on Japan and China - many fragmentary
  - 1. Lecture on Ainos of Yezo - typed. (Box 1)
  - 2. Notes on travels in Japan - from Osaka to Kaya-San with lists of expenses - in manuscript. (Box 1)
  - 3. Notes on burial mounds of Japan, on "pit-dwellers," on Shinto and religious beliefs of Japanese; Buddhism in Japan; lecture on Shinto temples and Buddhist temples. (Box 1)
  - 4. Map of Yezo - hand drawn, artist not given. 16" x 20 1/2". (Box 1)
  - 5. Aino myth. (Box 1)
  - 6. Descriptions on his travels in Yezo. (Box 1)
  - 7. Descriptions of travels in China. (Box 1)
  - 8. Typed notes on history of Chinese. (Box 1)
  - 9. Notes for a slide lecture on the Ainos. (Box 1)